<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.13">
  <compounddef id="indexpage" kind="page">
    <compoundname>index</compoundname>
    <title>Index Preamble and License</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><simplesect kind="author"><para>Jaroslav Kysela <ulink url="mailto:perex@perex.cz">perex@perex.cz</ulink> </para></simplesect>
<simplesect kind="author"><para>Abramo Bagnara <ulink url="mailto:abramo@alsa-project.org">abramo@alsa-project.org</ulink> </para></simplesect>
<simplesect kind="author"><para>Takashi Iwai <ulink url="mailto:tiwai@suse.de">tiwai@suse.de</ulink> </para></simplesect>
<simplesect kind="author"><para>Frank van de Pol <ulink url="mailto:fvdpol@coil.demon.nl">fvdpol@coil.demon.nl</ulink></para></simplesect>
<heading level="2">Preface</heading>
</para><para>The Advanced Linux Sound Architecture (<emphasis>ALSA</emphasis>) comes with a kernel API and a library API. This document describes the library API and how it interfaces with the kernel API.</para><para><heading level="2">Documentation License</heading>
</para><para>This documentation is free; you can redistribute it without any restrictions. Modifications or derived work must retain the copyright and list all authors.</para><para>This documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</para><para><heading level="2">API usage</heading>
</para><para>Application programmers should use the library API rather than the kernel API. The library offers 100% of the functionality of the kernel API, but adds major improvements in usability, making the application code simpler and better looking. In addition, future fixes or compatibility code may be placed in the library code instead of the kernel driver.</para><para><heading level="2">API links</heading>
</para><para><itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="control" kindref="compound">Control interface</ref> explains the primitive controls API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="hcontrol" kindref="compound">High level control interface</ref> explains the high-level primitive controls API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="mixer" kindref="compound">Mixer interface</ref> explains the mixer controls API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="pcm" kindref="compound">PCM (digital audio) interface</ref> explains the design of the PCM (digital audio) API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="pcm_plugins" kindref="compound">PCM (digital audio) plugins</ref> explains the design of PCM (digital audio) plugins. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="pcm_external_plugins" kindref="compound">PCM External Plugin SDK</ref> explains the external PCM plugin SDK. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="ctl_external_plugins" kindref="compound">External Control Plugin SDK</ref> explains the external control plugin SDK. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="rawmidi" kindref="compound">RawMidi interface</ref> explains the design of the RawMidi API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="timer" kindref="compound">Timer interface</ref> explains the design of the Timer API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="seq" kindref="compound">Sequencer interface</ref> explains the design of the Sequencer API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="group__ucm" kindref="compound">Use Case Interface</ref> explains the use case API. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="group__topology" kindref="compound">ALSA Topology Interface</ref> explains the DSP topology API. </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para><para><heading level="2">Configuration</heading>
</para><para><itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="conf" kindref="compound">Configuration files</ref> explains the syntax of library configuration files. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="confarg" kindref="compound">Runtime arguments in configuration files</ref> explains the run-time argument syntax. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="conffunc" kindref="compound">Runtime functions in configuration files</ref> explains run-time function definitions and their usage. </para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Page <ref refid="confhooks" kindref="compound">Hooks in configuration files</ref> explains run-time hook definitions and their usage. </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
